Guide to the Charles E. Bigelow and Bay State Shoe Factory Papers circa 1840-1939 MS 3110
New-York Historical Society
Charles E. Bigelow papers
circa 1840-1939
New-York Historical Society
MS 3110
23 Linear feet in 23 record cartons
Personal papers of Charles Bigelow (1851-1939), including family correspondence, photographs, and househould records; as well as business papers for the Bay State Shoe Factory. Includes financial records, factory reports, business correspondence, and legal documents.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
TBD
Biographical / Historical
TBD Ce Bigelow married Isabella Lyall Dean, widow of Louis Dean, in 1893
Immediate Source of Acquisition
TBD
Related Materials
TBD
Scope and Contents
TBD
- Series I: Bigelow Family papers, 1840-1930
  - Bigelow family correspondence, 1840-1924 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Bigelow family invitations and calling cards, 1870-1900 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Bigelow family invitations and calling cards, 1905-1925 (Box 5, Folder 5-9)
  - Bigelow family address book, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Bigelow family RSVPs and thank you notes, 1900-1925 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Bigelow family photographs, scrapbooks, and clippings, 1860-1930 (Box 8, Folder 1-9)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes family portraits, snapshots, stereographs, cabinet cards, clippings, and a handmade scrapbook. Some photographs are identified with names and dates.
  - C.D. Bigelow correspondence and papers, 1850-1881 (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
  - C.E. Bigelow correspondence, 1860-1892 (Box 1, Folder 14-19)
  - C.E. Bigelow correspondence, 1877-1931 (Box 2, Folder 1-13)
  - C.E. Bigelow correspondence, 1860-1875 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - C.E. Bigelow correspondence, 1869-1873 (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
    Letters from Bigelow's time at Yale
  - C.E. Bigelow correspondence, 1869-1873 (Box 4, Folder 1-12)
    Letters from Bigelow's time at Yale.
  - C.E. Bigelow household account books, 1856-1918 (Box 13, Folder 1-9)
  - C.E. Bigelow household account books, 1880-1905 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - C.E. Bigelow household bills and receipts, 1870-1899 (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
  - C.E. Bigelow household bills and receipts, 1900-1912 (Box 10, Folder 1-17)
  - C.E. Bigelow household bills and receipts, 1913-1939 (Box 11, Folder 1-5)
  - C.E. Bigelow personal finance and investments, 1875-1915 (Box 11, Folder 6-11)
  - C.E. Bigelow personal finance and investments-Mining, 1876-1883 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - C.E. Bigelow personal finance and investments-Mining, 1880-1899 (Box 12, Folder 3-8)
  - C.E. Bigelow personal finance and investments-Real estate deeds, 1860-1880 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - C.E. Bigelow telegraph code books, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Travel ephemera, 1880-1930 (Box 14, Folder 1-14)
    China, Japan, steamship lines, L'exposition de Beaux Arts 1882, Italy, England, Switzerland, Spain, Germany, Algeria, Morocco, Tunisia, Palestine, Syria, Yellowstone Park
  - Yale University-related ephemera, 1867-1926 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
    Printed materials, alumni directories,and photographs, mainly related to C.E. Bigelow and his Yale class of 1873.
  - Yale University-related ephemera, 1869-1929 (Box 7, Folder 1-13)
    Ephemera related to C.E. Bigelow and his Yale class of 1873. Includes notes, compositions, academic prizes, and programs from dances and other social events from Bigelow's time at Yale (1869-1873). Other material is related to Bigleow's activities with the Yale Alumni Association.
- Series II: Bay State Shoe and Leather Company papers, 1870-1935
  - Business correspondence, circa 1896-1900 (Box 8)
  - Bay State Shoe Factory records, 1870s-1890s (Box 5)
    Leather samples, canvas samples, correspondence, printed materials
  - Bay State Shoe factory records, 1870s-1890s (Box 6)
  - Bay State Shoe & Leather Co. papers (Box 1 of 7), circa 1880-1920 (Box 15)
    Pamphlets, samples from shoe factory (including government reports on prison manufacturing), financial documents, business correspondence.
  - Bay State Shoe & Leather Co. papers (Box 2 of 7), circa 1880-1920 (Box 16)
  - Bay State Shoe & Leather Co. papers (Box 3 of 7), circa 1880-1920 (Box 17)
  - Bay State Shoe & Leather Co. papers (Box 4 of 7), circa 1880-1920 (Box 18)
  - Bay State Shoe & Leather Co. papers (Box 5 of 7), circa 1880-1920 (Box 19)
  - Bay State Shoe & Leather Co. papers (Box 6 of 7), circa 1880-1920 (Box 20)
  - Bay State Shoe & Leather Co. papers (Box 7 of 7), circa 1880-1920 (Box 21)
  - Commonwealth Shoe & Leather: Boston; Related to Bay State Papers, Old Colony Boot & Shoe (Box 1 of 2), circa 1895-1910 (Box 12)
    Business correspondence, financal documents, legal documents, factory reports (postcards)
  - Commonwealth Shoe & Leather: Boston; Related to Bay State Papers, Old Colony Boot & Shoe (Box 2 of 2), circa 1895-1910 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous bills & receipts (Box 1 of 2), 1890s-1930s (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous bills & receipts (Box 2 of 2), 1890s-1930s (Box 4)
- Series III: Other Businesses, 1870-1930
  - Beaconlamp Raritan Electric Manufacturing Co. papers, circa 1898-1905 (Box 10)
    Business correspondence, financial records
  - Lyall & Reinsburg papers; Art collection; Business; Biographical, 1870s-1930s (Box 14)
    Legal Documents, Financial documents, Business correspondence, correspondence, documents (German)